<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The marchant A sermon preached at Paules Crosse on Sunday the 24. of August, being the day before Bartholomew faire. 1607. By Daniell Price Master of Arts, of Exeter Colledge in Oxford.</title>
            <author>Price, Daniel, 1581-1631.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1608</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 73 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10050</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20296</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115212</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850431</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850431</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15633</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10050)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15633)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1331:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The marchant A sermon preached at Paules Crosse on Sunday the 24. of August, being the day before Bartholomew faire. 1607. By Daniell Price Master of Arts, of Exeter Colledge in Oxford.</title>
                  <author>Price, Daniel, 1581-1631.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 31, 34-38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Ioseph Barnes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1608.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15633:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15633:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE MARCHANT.</hi> A SERMON PREACHED AT PAVLES Croſſe on Sunday the 24. of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt, being the day before <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholomew faire.</hi>
1607.</p>
            <p>BY DANIELL PRICE <hi>Master of Arts, of Exeter Colledge in Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>Oxford crest</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>At Oxford,</hi> Printed by Ioſeph Barnes. 1608.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:15633:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15633:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONORABLE Companie of Merchants of the Citie of London.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Onourable, worſhipfull, &amp; belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, at the last I am come to the execution of my firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to the dedication of this Croſſe labour. It was long ſince prepared for you, and now at the length preſented vnto you, the Lord giue all of you a ſpirituall bleſſing by it. Some honourable, and many favourable gales of winde haue at length brought home this
<hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant</hi> vnto you, though in my labour in conducting ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, I haue ventured my credit to the wide ſea of common opinion. I confeſſe it is not the <hi>Merchant Royall</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to <hi>Salomon,</hi> laden with gold, and ſilver, ivory, and apes and Peacocks: But yet is ſuch a
<hi>Merchant</hi> as <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> in all his riches was not ſo great as he. It is a holie and heavenly Merchant carefull in ſearch, happy in ſucceſſe whom neither the tediouſneſſe of the way, nor difficultie of the ſtraites could hinder, but that he paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth through the worlds Ocean, with ſpeede, and gaine, and glorie, Chriſt being his Pilot, faith his ſterne, hope
<pb facs="tcp:15633:3"/>his ancor, Conſcience his carde, good works his lading, happineſſe his landing, and his haven heaven.</p>
            <p>At that great Marte whereas I was commaunded this buſineſse I fitted the time with this Text, I hope this Text fitted ſome of you at that time, and my praier vnto God ſhall be that you may be fitted by this vnto the attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of your eternall ſalvation, and ſo I commend theſe labours vnto you, and your ſelues and them vnto God.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From Exeter Colledge</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>this 20. of Aprill. 1608.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Yours in the Lord Ieſus <hi>DANIEL PRICE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:15633:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Matth. 13.45.46.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>The kingdome of heaven is like to a Merchant man, that ſeeketh good Pearles, who having found a Pearle of great price, went &amp; ſould all that he had, and bought it.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honourable, Right Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipful, &amp; the reſt right welbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued in the Lorde, yee are all heere preſent before God, to heare al things that are this day commanded by God, the Lord bleſſe you al, and encreaſe the number of Chriſtian, faithfull, diligent, &amp; obedient hearers. Jt is not long ſince that (being commanded to this place) in a more privat au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,<note place="margin">Hol. 1.2.3.</note> I propoſed vnto you a Text that contained the ſumme of the Law, and Goſpel, nature and grace, ſinne and righteouſneſſe, life and death, Iudgement &amp; mercie, affliction and converſion, adverſity cauſing man to returne to God, and repentance cauſing God to turne vnto man; which ſubiect I had now followed but that this time and meeting, and the expectatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſo great an aſſembly doe challenge this daie, ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſcourſe: And therefore I haue, (as you heare) provided a text of trafique, and trading, of buying, and ſelling, of merchandiſe, and marting, of gayning, and bargaining, an example of a good merchant, of good merchandiſe, of good policie, of good pietie, of a <hi>roial exchange,</hi> nay more, of a holy &amp; heave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>lie exchange; <hi>The kingdome of heaven is like to a marchant man, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Saviour in this Chapter by ſeaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> parables ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb facs="tcp:15633:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>forth the ſtate of the kingdome of heauen, by the <hi>ſeed, ver.</hi> 3. of the <hi>tares, verſ.</hi> 24. of the
<hi>muſtard ſeede, verſ.</hi> 31. of the <hi>leaven, verſ.</hi> 33. of the <hi>treaſure, verſ.</hi> 44. of a <hi>net, verſ.</hi> 47. and here of a <hi>merchant</hi> in this 45. herein ſhewing the Miniſters of the Goſpell their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, left to them in performance of their calling, not only nakedly to lay open the trueth, but alſo to vſe helps of wit, invention and art, the good gifts of God, which may be vſed in Similitudes, Alluſions, Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, Compariſons, Proverbs, and Parables which tend to edification and illuſtrating of the word, that ſo the weake may be comforted, the rude may be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed the drowſie may be awakened, the hard-har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed may be ſuppled, the perverſe overwhelmed, and ſo by al meanes God himſelfe may be glorified, &amp; the Hearers bettered. S. <hi>Paule,</hi> the Doctor of the Gentiles profeſſeth of himſelfe <hi>that he became all, vnto all men, that he might by all meares,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor.
9.2.</note> 
               <hi>win ſome of all.</hi> More truly may it bee ſpoken of
<hi>Chriſt</hi> who was the Schoolema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of this maſter of the Gentiles he became all vnto al men, not only as he was ſent <hi>Diues diuitibus, pauper pauperibus, flens fle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tibus, eſuriens eſurientibus, ſitiens ſitientibus,</hi> Rich vnto thoſe that are rich, poore vnto thoſe that are poore, weeping to thoſe that are wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, hungry to thoſe that are hungry, thirſty to thoſe that are thirſty,<note place="margin">Ambroſeir
4. Luc.</note> as S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>medicus ad ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grotos, redemptor ad vendites, ad errantes via, ad mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuos vita,</hi> a Phiſitian to thoſe that are ſicke, a ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſomer to thoſe that were ſould, the way to thoſe that did wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, the life to thoſe that were dead; as S.
<hi>Bernard,</hi> but becauſe he is truly <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Cor. 15.</note> even al in all as S.
<pb facs="tcp:15633:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Paule</hi> ſpeaketh,<note n="a" place="margin">1. Cor. 15.28.</note> and even al to al in that he ſeeketh to draw al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by the very ſimilituds drawne from their trades of life. So hee called the wiſe Aſtronomers of the Eaſt by a ſtar.<note n="b" place="margin">Math. 2 10</note> He drew the Fiſhermen vnto him by a draught of fiſh,<note n="c" place="margin">Luk. 5.6.</note> the <hi>Samaritane</hi> that came to draw water at <hi>Iacobs</hi> wel hee drew by drawing for her the waters of life.<note n="d" place="margin">Ioh. 4.14.</note> To <hi>Marie</hi> in the garden he appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red like the gardner?<note n="e" place="margin">Ioh
20.15</note> To the travellers his diſciples he appeared like a traveller.<note n="f" place="margin">Luk, 24, 16</note> So alſo frequently in the Goſpel he teacheth many by manie exemplarie ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litudes, the rich man by the rich mans care &amp; greedie gathering, the Vine dreſſer by the vine dreſſers dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, and hedging, and dreſſing, The Labourer by the Labourers hire and working, the builder by the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders laying good foundation, the huſbandman by the huſbandmans ſowing, the fiſherman by the fiſherma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s caſting nets and drawing: and here the merchant ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the merchants buying and ſelling, <hi>Quibus exemplis Doctores Evangelij monentur,</hi> by which examples the teachers of the Goſpel are admoniſhed as <hi>Muſculus</hi> obſerueth, to become al vnto al, not only as <hi>S. Paule,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Muſ. in 4. Matth.</note> 
               <hi>qui omnium ingenijs ſe acomodovit,</hi> who did apply him ſelfe to the capacities of all hearers whatſoeuer, or howſoeuer different as <hi>Piſeator</hi> obſerveth, but euen as my Text maſter <hi>verbu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vitea &amp; vita verbi</hi> the word of life,<note place="margin">Piſcator.</note> and the life of the word who ſpake as neuer ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpake, by framing themſelues to al mens knowledge and nature as he did by allegories, ſtories, parables, &amp; what not. Which may for euer ſerue to ſtoppe the mouthes of thoſe traducing and ignorant <hi>Scepticks</hi> who vilifie the ingenious endeavours, of the beſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing
<pb facs="tcp:15633:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>laboures in Gods vinyard, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they be fitted for the daie, times, place, perſons, or other circumſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, with ſtories of huſbandrie from <hi>Columella,</hi> axioms of philoſophie from
<hi>Ariſtotle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pet. Mart in 1. Cor. 15. Hem Com. in Tit. 1.12. Piſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. in Tit. 1
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. Cal. in. Cor
15.33.</note> aphoriſmes of <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick</hi> from <hi>Galen,</hi> maximes of <hi>Law</hi> from <hi>Iuſtinian,</hi> ſo vſing <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> &amp; <hi>Tully</hi> for force of ſpeech, <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> for Similies,
<hi>Lyvie</hi> for hiſtorian eloquence, <hi>Virgil</hi> for deſcriptions,
<hi>Tacitus</hi> for wit, <hi>Seneca</hi> for excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of humanitie, &amp;
<hi>Plutarch</hi> for moralitie. Sure J am that profound <hi>Auſtin</hi> in his queſtions, learned <hi>Ierome</hi> in his expoſitions, patheticall
<hi>Chriſostome</hi> in his ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications, melifluent <hi>Bernard</hi> in his meditations, pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie <hi>Cyprian</hi> in his perſwaſions, ſweet
<hi>Ambroſe</hi> in his alluſions, eloquent <hi>Nazianzen</hi> in mouing affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions doe make good vſe of theſe writings, knowing that
<hi>Quodcun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſcriptum est &amp;c.</hi> whatſoever is written before time is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for our learning, as for example in this Text wherin (as in al parables Chriſt applyeth them to heauenly vſes ſo more eſpecially in this) he implieth thus much, that if a Marchant in his worldly vocation doth ſo continuallie follow his trade in ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, finding, buying, ſelling, &amp; exchanging; how much more ſhould a Chriſtian labour in his profeſſion, and in his converſation to runne his race, to fight his fight, to finiſh his courſe? And if the marchant doe ſo much trauel for the attaining of a pearle, how much ſhould a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> labour for the precious pearle of his ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The K. of heauen is like vnto a marchant ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp;c.</hi> which is (as you ſee Ho, Worſhipful &amp; beloued) a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable for the
<hi>Author</hi> moſt bleſſed, for the <hi>matter</hi> moſt gracious, for the <hi>example</hi> of the marchant moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous,
<pb facs="tcp:15633:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>for the <hi>marcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>diſe</hi> moſt glorious, for the <hi>gaine</hi> moſt deſirous, more to be deſired then gold, yea then fine gold.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e of heauen is like to a man,</hi> not to everie man but to a marchant man, not to everie marchant but to a marchant that ſeeketh pearles, nether to one that ſeeketh al kind of pearles, but to a marchant that ſeeketh good pearles, nether to one that onlie ſeeketh but findeth, and hauing found ſelleth, and hauing ſould buieth, and hauing bought exchangeth manie good pearles for one, naie all his good pearles for one goodlie pearle, a pearle of great price, and ſo you ſee that the kingdome of heauen is compared to a wiſe diligent, ſeeking, finding, buying, ſelling, exchanging marchant.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The K. of heauen is like to a marchant &amp;c.</hi> Beloued the action of this marchant is not for anie ſmal, but for great gaine, not for anie carnal, but for ſpirituall glorie, not for anie tranſitorie, but for an eternal trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. <hi>The K. of heauen is like to a marchant &amp;c.</hi> VVhat trade more honorable then the marchant, what mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe more honorable then the Kingdome of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auen? Yee are manie of you come hether as buiers, as ſellers, as marchants, and therfore at this time what argument more ſuaſible, more plauſible, more force<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, more available then this
<hi>the K. of heauen is like to a marchant?</hi> like to a ſeking, finding, buying, ſelling, exchanging marchant.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Diuiſio </seg>
               </label> In theſe words J wil obſerue theſe two general points 1. the difficultie of obtaining the Kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timated in that it is compared to a marchant, the moſt
<pb facs="tcp:15633:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>diligent, careful, aſſiduous, induſtrious, laborious, and indefatigable of al other kinds of life. 2. The earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes required in purſuing this kingdome expreſſed in the ſeeking, finding, buying, ſelling, exchanging al.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Subdiuiſio. </seg>
               </label> In the 1. obſeru. 1. the thing compared. <hi>The king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heaven.</hi> 2. The thing to the which it is compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. <hi>Is like to a Merchant man.</hi> In the 2. obſerue 1. the wiſdome in ſeeking, <hi>who ſeeketh good pearles,</hi> 2. his ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe in finding, <hi>VVho having found a pearle of great price,</hi>
3. his deere purchaſe in obtaining, <hi>went and ſold all that he had and bought it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe be the limits of my paſſage, the land markes of my merchant, the particulers to be entreated of at this time and the proper circumſtances of text. The Lord bleſſe me in ſpeaking, and you in hearing, &amp; giue vs al a true vnderſtanding in al things in Chriſt Ieſus. Firſt of the firſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. The thing compared.</note> In Scripture we had read of many and ſundry king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes; of the K. of Sathan, the K. of the world, the K. of Antichriſt, the K. of Chriſt, the kingdome of God, the kingdome of heauen. The kingdome of Sathan be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing that tyrannical regencie, by which the Prince of darkneſſe ruleth in the children of diſobedience. The K. of Antichriſt whereby the Pope the <hi>ille ipſe iſte An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tichristus</hi> doth by his falſe doctrine, blinde and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards binde the children of darkneſſe to bee obedient to him: The kingdome of the worlde is properly that humane gouernment by which one or diuers doe by Gods ordinance, direct and gouerne the children of men. The K. of God, or of Chriſt, or of heauen, is that ſpiritual gouernment begunne in euery of the elect in
<pb facs="tcp:15633:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>this life, by the glory of grace, and fully accompliſhed in the life to come by the grace of glory. There is much difference betweene the regime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of theſe king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, the gouernment of Sathans kingdome Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical, of Antichriſt Papiſtical, of the world Politicall, of heauen ſpiritual. Nay there is much difference eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amongſt the kingdomes of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as they bee ſubdiuided in the K. of the world.
<hi>Aventinus</hi> in his <hi>bello Turico</hi> could obſerue that the Empire of <hi>Germany</hi> was <hi>regnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> regum,</hi> a kingdome of kings, becauſe there were ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny princes in that dominion that the kingdome of
<hi>France</hi> was <hi>regnum aſinorum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aventi. bell. Ture.</note> a kingdome of aſſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the many taxes and grieuous burthens they endured that the K. of <hi>Spaine</hi> was <hi>Regnum hominum,</hi> a kingdome of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe they are ſo obedient to their prince. That the K. of <hi>England,</hi> was <hi>Regnum Diaboloru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> a kingdome of Diuels, becauſe the ſubiect, had ſo oft proued Traitors and betraied &amp; depriued their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. If the kingdome of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> differ ſo much, how much doth the kingdome of God differ from men. The K. of this world, from the kingdome of the world to come, the kingdome of earth, from the kingdome of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? For this kingdome is that whereof Chriſt is the king, the Chriſtians the ſubiects, the laws the word, the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers the Preachers, the vicegerents the governours, the enemies of this kingdome, ſinne, ſathan, death and damnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the weapons of this kingdome praier, faith hope, and charitie. The place of this kingdome, this world, and the world to come, the continuance of this kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e for euer &amp; euer. It is a prepared<note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 25 44</note> kingdome. It is an eternal kingdome,<note n="b" place="margin">2 Pet 11.</note> it is a bleſſed kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e,<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uc.
14.15</note> it is
<pb facs="tcp:15633:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>a heauenly kingdome.<note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 24.34</note> It is a powerful kingdome, a glorious kingdome, an everlaſting kingdome, for his is the kingdome the power and the glory, for euer and euer, Amen.</p>
            <p>In ſcripture it is diuerſlie taken,<note place="margin">Cal. in Mat 2.3. Mar. in. Math. 18. 1. Beza in Math. 5.20.</note> ſometimes <hi>pro re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutione ad Beatam vitam,</hi> as Maſter <hi>Calvin;</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<hi>pro Eccleſiae renovatione,</hi> as <hi>Marlorat,</hi> ſomtimes <hi>pro immortalitate Dei filijs promiſsa,</hi> as Maſter <hi>Beza;</hi> here it is taken <hi>pro Eccleſia,</hi> as the Commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gloſſe, <hi>pro Eccleſia milita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti,</hi> as <hi>Carthuſian, pro Evangelij predica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione</hi> as
<hi>Lyra, pro Notitia ſcripturarum,</hi> as <hi>Aquinas,</hi> moſt properly for the Goſpel as the current of Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters doe runne; for this is that light of the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>thorne of Jſrael, the knowledge of the Aphoriſmes of Chriſt, the wiſdome of the Croſſe, the Beacon of the ſoule, the Cubit of the Sanctuarie, the Glad tydings the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of God to ſalvation, and the Encyclopaedia of al knowledge;<note place="margin">Hugo.</note> becauſe
<hi>Quicquid in eo docetur veritas, quicquid praecipitur bonitas, quicquid promittitur foeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citas eſt; Quia Deus veritas eſt ſine falacia, bonitas ſine malitia foelicitas ſine miſeria.</hi> Whatſoeuer is taught herin is truth, whatſoeuer is commanded is goodnes whatſoeuer is promiſed is perfect happines &amp;c.</p>
            <p>It is a miſterie 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1. a miſterie hid from the beginning of the world. <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.9. the revelation, of this miſterie
<hi>Rom.</hi> 16.25. Jt is a new couenant <hi>Ier.</hi> 3.31. Jt is the adminiſtration of the ſpirit.<note place="margin">Clem. Alex. 1. ſtromat.</note> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.8. Clemens Alexandrinus obſerueth in the
1 of his <hi>Stromato<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> that the law was a ſchoolmaſter to the Hebrues &amp; philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy a ſchoolmaſter to the Grecians before Chriſt, but after the comming of Chriſt, the law and Philoſophy
<pb facs="tcp:15633:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>became handmaids of the Goſpel, and the Goſpel was the only ſchoolemaſter to the Jews &amp; Gentiles, to the Grecians and Barbarians, bond, and free, Law &amp; Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy being ſubiect to the Goſpell, as <hi>Agar</hi> &amp; <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maell</hi> to
<hi>Sara.</hi> And therefore well may the Goſpell bee called the K. of heauen, becauſe it is the meanes to bring Chriſtians to the K. of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: ſo that the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine I obſerue out of theſe firſt words is this.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> That the knowledge of the Goſpel is to a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen vpon earth. The reaſon of this I drawe <hi>a minore,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
               </label> as the Schooles ſpeake, if the law were ſo ſweet &amp; pleaſant &amp; delightſome vnto man, how much more ſhoulde the Goſpell? Now of the Law <hi>David</hi> thus ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.8.</note> the Law of the Lord is powerful conuerting the ſoule. The teſtimony of the Lord is ſure, and giueth light vnto the ſimple. The ſtatutes of the Lord be right, &amp; reioice the heart. The commandements of the Lord be pure, &amp; giue light to the eies. The feare of the Lord is cleane, and endureth for euer. The iudgmentes of the Lord are true and righteous altogither, more to be deſired then gold, yea then fine gold, ſweeter alſo then the hony and the hony combe. <hi>Pſalme.</hi> 19.8. How much more the Goſpell that was not deliuered with thundring or lightning, or trembling, or with the Trumpets ſounding, or with the earth quaking, but was deliuered by God, receiued by Angels, proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to ſhepheards, preached by fiſhers, &amp; yet ſo ioie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully deliuered, receiued, proclaimed, preached, as that all the hoſt of heauen, the ſweete ſinging quire of Cherubins, at the receiuing of it ſang that Angelicall and Evangelical hymne, <hi>Gloria in excelſis,</hi> Glory be to
<pb facs="tcp:15633:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>God on high, in earth peace, good will towards men. No man I hope doubteth of the ſupremacy, &amp; ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eminency of the Goſpell, hauing ſuch comforts and ioies, and pleaſures, as it is receiued by men, and ſuch exceeding authority as it is receiued from God write<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the finger of God, revealed by the will of God, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired by the ſpirit of God, pronounced by the mouth of God, and proclaimed by the power of God, the knowledge of the goſpell, being the knowledge of C. the knowledge of C. being life eternall, and life eternal being the K. of heauen. This made a father thus to ſpeake, <hi>Nihil in hac vita dulcius ſentitur, nihil avi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius ſumitur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iugo li. 30. de Anima.</note> 
               <hi>nihilita me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tem ab amore mundi ſeparat, nihil ſic animum co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra tentationes roborat, nihil it a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> excitat ad omne opus bonum.</hi> Nothing in this life is more ſweetly affected, nothing more earneſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, nothing doth ſo fortefie the ſoule, againſt the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults of temptation. Nothing doth ſo excite a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and aſſiſt him, in the performance of any good worke.<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> The vſe of this doctrine is to incite al that are the ſonnes of the moſt high, to the due embracing of this heauenly bleſſing, of this holy, and happy know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. And ſurely euerie man ſhould bee ſo much the more earneſt in ſeeking this kingdome, as the hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers are violent in oppoſing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues againſt our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual deſire in this, for we ſhal finde the fleſh ready to infect, the world ready to withdrawe, the wicked rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to diſturbe thoſe that deſire to bee Citizens of that Celeſtial Jeruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it ſhall much moue the true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian to the purſuit of this glory, if he doe but conſider the common backſliding, and hypocritical profeſſing
<pb facs="tcp:15633:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>of many who doe ſerue to affect this knowledge, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a name as the Church of <hi>Sardis,</hi> hauing a name that they are aliue, when they are dead.<note place="margin">Ana<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>harſis</note> 
               <hi>Anacharſis</hi> told the
<hi>Athenians,</hi> that they vſed their mony to no other end, but to nomber with all, ſo ſure may it bee ſaid of many, that they vſe the goſpell, but only for a ſhew, only for a name. They can crie, <hi>Templum Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini, Templum Domini,</hi> and yet wilbe ready to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute <hi>Dominum templi,</hi> they ſeeme to be as <hi>Aaron,</hi> but are as <hi>Abiram,</hi> to be as <hi>Simon Peter,</hi> but be indeed as <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> to be as
<hi>Paule</hi> a Doctor of the Gentiles when they be but as <hi>Saule,</hi> a perſecutor of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, to carry the name of <hi>Iuda,</hi> &amp; the minde of <hi>Iudas.</hi> The name of <hi>Cephas,</hi> the minde of
<hi>Cayphas,</hi> and ſo are become as backſliding <hi>Ephramites,</hi> or as rebellious <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites,</hi> or as reuolting <hi>Apostats,</hi> turning the grace of God into wantonnes, by their bare and naked &amp; earth creeping hypocritical profeſſion. Beloued, beware of ſuch, and ſet your deſires be harty in purity of minde, chriſtianly in conuerſation of manners, and entirely without faigned diſſembling. Let euery one of you co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet theſe ſpiritual things, it ſhal not be any vſurpation if euerie Chriſtian, in a ſpirituall ambition, ſeeke this kingdome, and deſire to bee entitled with the name of a king, for as <hi>Greg.</hi> obſerueth,
<hi>Optime Sancti viri ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crae ſcripturae teſtimonio reges vocantur quia praelati cunctis motibus carnis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg.</note> 
               <hi>modo luxuriae appetitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> infra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, modo aeſtum avaritiae temperant, modo gloriam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinant, modo ſuggeſtiones obruu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t modo igne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> furoris ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingunt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gregorie,</note> Worthyly are holy men called by the name of kings, by the Teſtimony of the holy Scripture be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:15633:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>of reſiſting the motions of the fleſh, ſometimes bridling their luxurious appetites, ſometimes tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering the heat of their couetous deſires, ſometimes humbling their glorie, ſometimes repreſſing the ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions of the fleſh, ſometimes extinguiſhing the fire of their anger. Let me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> remember that God hath made them ſpiritual kings, and therefore they walke wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of their calling, ſwaying their thoughts, ruling their wils, ordering their affections, correcting their corruptions, and managing all their actions, that ſo by the looſenes of their liues, the blindnes of their minds, the rebellion of their affections, they become not ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants vnto ſin, ſo ſhall euery of you obtaine that king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome where the K. is Verity, the Law Charity, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour equitie, the peace felicitie, the life eternitie, euen the K. of heauen, which is here compared to the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, My ſecond obſeruation</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The kingdome of heaven is like to a Merchant man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſeru. </seg>2</label> If that complaint were true, which
<hi>Eraſmus</hi> tooke vp in his time againſt marchants, it is a meruaile why J ſhould compare the K. of heauen, to a merchant, when ſo few merchants are like to the kingdome of heauen. His words are theſe. <hi>Negotiatorum genus ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil habet ſacram praeter vnum pecuniae lucrum, cui ſe totos ſeu deo conſecrarunt; hoc pietatem, hoc amicitiam, hoc honestum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eraſm.</note> 
               <hi>hoc famam, hoc diuina pariter &amp; huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na omnia metiuntur.</hi> The trade of marchants account nothing good or holy, but only the only lucre of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, for the attaining of which they haue dedicated, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrated themſelues as vnto God, by this they mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure piety, amity, honeſtie, credit, and fame, and al hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine,
<pb facs="tcp:15633:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>and diuine things. I am ſure he ſpake by the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of ſome, in the name of al, for the ſtories, and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes of
<hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles, Grecians and Barbari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Infidels</hi> &amp;
<hi>Christians,</hi> doe acknowledge the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie, dignitie, &amp; excellencie of marchants,<note place="margin">Praiſe of the March.</note> &amp; they haue approued the marchant of al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to be the moſt diligent for his life, the moſt aſſiduous in his labour, the moſt aduenterous on the ſea, the moſt beneficiall to the land, the glorie of his countrie, and the beſt pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of his common wealth. The word in the original is
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> tranſlated by ſome <hi>mercator,</hi> by ſome
<hi>Negoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator. Caeſar</hi> maketh a difference betweene <hi>Mercator,</hi> and <hi>Negotiator,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heſich. Caeſar. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Iunius.</note> &amp; <hi>Iunius</hi> affirmeth it <hi>videntur differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re in hoc quod mercator domicilium, &amp; familiam habet negotiator peregrinatur incertas ſedes permutans.</hi> The words differ in this; that <hi>mercator</hi> hath a houſe &amp; fami<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lie, <hi>negotiator</hi> is, he that ſtil trauaileth, voiageth, vent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treth, changing his ſeates tike the true Chriſtian, who is euer trauailing to change his countrie, knowing that here he hath noe abiding citie, but doth ſeeke on to <hi>come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gloſſe ſheweth, whie this kingdome is for our inſtruction compared to the marcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.<note place="margin">Gloſſe. Ord.</note> 
               <hi>Quia debemus omnes intellige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do certe, &amp; operando bene nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiari.</hi> Becauſe we ought by right vnderſtanding &amp; by good practiſing to negotiate. There be 2. things to be obſerued in the marchant, the profit,<note place="margin">2. Things. Profit. Danger.</note> and the danger of the Trade, of the profit we ſhal find what great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie came of
<hi>Salomon,</hi> by the Triennial comming of the Nauie of <hi>Tharſhis,</hi> that brought vnto him gold, and ſiluer, I vorie, and apes, and Peacoks, euen
<pb facs="tcp:15633:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>al things, for profit, and for pleaſure 1.
<hi>Kings.</hi> 10.22. where the holy Ghoſt doth ſhew, that this trade was the occaſion of the inriching of <hi>Salomon,</hi> And ſurely it doth mutually inrich al kingdomes, making the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per commodities of one countrie commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to another Witneſſe our gold from <hi>India,</hi> our ſpices, from
<hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bia,</hi> our ſilkes from <hi>Spaine,</hi> our wines from
<hi>France,</hi> &amp; ſo many other commodities from other countries, wherby the marchant is the Key of the land, the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer of the kingdome, the venter of his ſoiles ſurplaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadge, the combiner of nations, &amp; the adamantine chain of Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries. of the daunger <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeaketh in the Pſalme, They that goe downe to the ſea in ſhipps and marchandiſe in great waters, theſe men ſee the workes of the Lord, and his wonders in the deepe, for at his word, the ſtormie windes ariſe, which lifte vp the waues therof, they are carried vp to heauen, and downe againe to the deepe, their ſoule melteth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in them, and al their cuning is gone <hi>Pſal.</hi>
107.22. &amp;c. Which peril and danger of them was the cauſe that
<hi>Pittacus</hi> held that ſea aduenturers, were neither a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the liuing, nor the dead, but did hang betweene both,<note place="margin">Virg. Aen.</note>
               <hi>Nauigantes ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> inter viuos nec mortuos,</hi> for if once the windes did ariſe, <hi>Vna euruſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> notuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ruunt,</hi> The eaſt and the weaſt, the north and the ſouth winds blowe, then be the keele neuer ſo ſtrong, the ribbs ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo ſtiffe, the chleets &amp; clampes neuer ſo faſt ſet on, yet if the tempeſt ariſe al is enda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gered, if a ioint crack al is hazared if a planke ſhoot vp al is gon. <hi>Quamuis Pontica pinus ſiluae filia nobilis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Horat. Od.</note> though the frame ſhould be of pine tree, nay though it ſhould be as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="tcp:15633:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>a Nauie as that of <hi>Tyrus</hi> in
<hi>Eſec.</hi> though the bords were of firre trees of <hi>Shenir,</hi> the maſts of the <hi>Cedars</hi> of <hi>Lybanus,</hi> the oares of the
<hi>Oakes</hi> of <hi>Baſan</hi> the banks of the <hi>Ivorie</hi> of
<hi>Chittin,</hi> the ſailes of the imbroidred linen of <hi>Egypt.</hi> Though they of <hi>Sidon,</hi> &amp; <hi>Arvad,</hi> were her
<hi>marriners,</hi> the wiſe in <hi>Tyrus</hi> her <hi>Pilots,</hi> the Antie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of <hi>Gebal</hi> her <hi>Calkers,</hi> yet they, their riches, and Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and Pilots, and Calkers, and Marchants, &amp; men of warre, may be ouerthrowne, periſh, ſunke, diſperſed and come to a feareful ruine. So that of all men J may ſaie with <hi>Dauid,</hi> theſe men ſee the workes of the Lord and his wounders in the deep. And ſurely ſo it is with the ſtate of the godly, in this life in moſt da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, ſubiect to the greateſt afliction, they are in the waues of the world, yet they aboue all others, ſee the works of the Lord and his wonders, in the deepeſt of their miſerie his power in deliuering them, his fauour in preſeruing them, his mercy in comforting them, his loue in care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, his care in protecting them, though with <hi>Paul</hi> they be in perils in the Citie, perils in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, perils amongſt falſe brethren, perils among his owne, perils in the ſea, as hee was moſt fearefully, the windes being contrary, the ſailing ieopardous. The voiage with hurt and much damage, not of the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, &amp; ſhip only but of their liues, the feareful winde
<hi>Euroclydon</hi> ariſing, that they were toſſed with an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Tempeſt, and that they ſawe neither ſun nor ſtarrs apearing for manie daies. Yet at length, a calme a ſunſhine, a <hi>Iubile</hi> ſhal come, he turneth awaie the ſtorme and the waues therof are ſtil, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are they qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eted and are glad, and he bringeth them to the hauen
<pb facs="tcp:15633:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>where they would be. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> The doctrine I obſerue out of the word <hi>Marchant,</hi> is this, that the ſtate of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian is not an idle vaine ſpeculation, but muſt bee a careful, painful, diligent, walking in his vocation.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
               </label> The reaſon of this doctrine, is proued a
<hi>Contrario</hi> by the <hi>Antitheſis</hi> betweene the ſtate of the Godlie, &amp; vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, vnder the name of the foole. The foole fouldeth his hands, and eateth vp his owne fleſh. Better is on ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, ſaith he with quietneſſe, then two handful with la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and vexation of ſpirit.<note place="margin">Prov.</note> But contrariwiſe, the wiſe <hi>Marchant,</hi> the true Chriſtian, he ſeeketh, he taketh paines, he laboureth, hee endeuoureth to follow hard to the marke, <hi>per Saxa per ignes currit mercator ad In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos,</hi> as the Poet ſpeaketh noe paines,<note place="margin">Horatius.</note> noe peril noe danger, noe coſt, noe temptation noe oppoſition can confront him.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> The vſe then of this doctrine, is to take heed of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaiding our ſelues, that eaſe &amp; quietneſſe is the beſt trade. <hi>Lepidus</hi> the heathen was taxt for a ſluggiſh &amp; idle fellow that ſiting laſie in the ſunne ſhine, cried out
<hi>vtinam hoc eſſe laborare!</hi> And ſo ſurely they that think Chriſtianity an idle kind of life, god ſhal laugh them to ſcorne, we al haue a goale, for which we muſt runne, we al haue propoſed to vs a garland for which we muſt wreſtle, we are al to haue a Crown, for which we muſt ſtriue, we are al <hi>Marriners,</hi> and we muſt ſaile in danger, before we come to the hauen of happines, we are al <hi>Trauailers,</hi> and we muſt toile before we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e to the Period of our iourney, which is
<hi>Paradiſe,</hi> wee are al <hi>labourers,</hi> we muſt indure the heate and burthen of the daie before we receaue our hire in heauen, wee
<pb facs="tcp:15633:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>are al <hi>ſouldiers,</hi> our
<hi>Tropheies</hi> be not celebrated till the victorie be atchieued, we are al
<hi>Merchants,</hi> we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not finde the Pearle of great price, vntill wee haue ſought for <hi>many good pearles.</hi> O the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> run, wraſtle, ſtriue, ſaile, toile, labour, fight the good fight, finiſh the courſe, ſeeke to be like to the good Merchant. <hi>The K. of heaven is like to a Merchant man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> The ſecond vſe of this Doctrine is more particuler, belonging only to thoſe that be Mercha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, that ſeeing the
<hi>Merchant</hi> here is ſo ſtudious, careful, diligent, and earneſt in good pearles, that euerie one of them ſeeke by al meanes to become heauenly
<hi>Merchants</hi> to ſeek, and labour, and endeauour to obtaine this Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, to lay vp his treaſure in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, where neither ruſt nor moath doth corrupt, &amp; where theeues break not through and ſteale, that as their trade of life is more honourable then others among men, ſo God ſhoulde be more honoured of them then of other men.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Ionas</hi> did flee from God, &amp; was detected by the voice of God himſelfe, in the lot, the Marriners raiſe as great a Tempeſt in the ſhip about <hi>Ionas,</hi> as was rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the ſea about the ſhip, and in that amaſedneſſe they diſchardge this peale of Gun-ſhot vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, what is thy <hi>fact,</hi> thy <hi>travell,</hi> thy
<hi>Country,</hi> thy <hi>people, whence comeſt thou?</hi> Nay more then all this, <hi>what is thy occupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi> Shewing in this exquiſite inquiſition, euen in their laſt interrogatorie, that euerie one ſhoulde haue ſome meanes, ſome art, ſome trade, ſome calling to liue.</p>
            <p>Jf manie about this Honorable Cittie ſhoulde bee aſked this queſtion, you ſhould finde an infinite nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15633:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>that walke in the Counſel of the vngodly, and ſtand in the way of ſinners, and ſit in the ſeate of ſcorners, able to anſwere no otherwiſe then <hi>Sathan</hi> did to God, that they liue by compaſſing the earth to, and fro, and by walking in it. They are vagrants, I may ſaie vaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonds, wandring perſons, as the
<hi>Planets</hi> in the Zodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ack, neuer keeping a fixed place. Of no endowment, imploiment, art or trade, or calling, or miſterie, vnleſſe they profeſſe the miſterie of iniquitie. <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon</hi> tooke notice of two ſo lewdly diſpoſed, &amp; tooke this order with them,<note place="margin">Plut.</note> 
               <hi>alterum è Macedonia fugere, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terum perſequi iuſsit,</hi> hee made one of them run out of the Countrey, and the other to driue him.</p>
            <p>Another ſort there bee as bad as theſe Coniurers, Charmers, Tellers of fortune, Robbers by land, Pyrats by ſea, Couſeners, Harlotts, Brokers, Vſerers, who by couſenadges, Impoſtures, fraudes, trickes, and circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, doe ſet at ſale, honeſtie, truth, conſcience, oathes, their ſoule and owne ſaluation. The ſumme of that I would ſpeake in this point if the time did ſerue is this, that euerie man ought to looke well, to the lawfulneſſe of his calling.<note place="margin">1. Cor.
12.</note> God hath giuen diuers gifts but the ſame ſpirit, he hath giuen diuerſities of ſpirits but the ſame Lord, he hath giuen to the
<hi>warriers</hi> a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to <hi>fight,</hi> to <hi>Counſellers</hi> a ſpirit to <hi>direct,</hi> to <hi>Iudges</hi> a ſpirit to diſcerne, to
<hi>magiſtrats</hi> a ſpirit to <hi>gouerne,</hi> to <hi>miniſters</hi> a ſpirit <hi>to conuince, to inſtruct, to reproue, to direct,</hi> to
<hi>Marcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts</hi> a ſpirit to <hi>trade, to traſique, to buy to ſell, to exchange, but of every one of them in their</hi> vocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he requireth that as he is holy, ſo they ſhould be holie. Wherefore beloued, ſeeing the Merchant in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15633:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>my Text, is by the ſinger of God particulerlie pointed at in this place, giue me leaue in one word, to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber you, that as your calling is honourable, and here your compariſon is honourable, in that you are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to the K. of heauen. O remember beloued, that if yee ſo much care, and labour, and trauel for earthlie things, how much more ought yee to care for ſpiritual things? I knowe not what reaſon manie learned men haue to condemne Merchants, and merchandiſe ſo much, that
<hi>Tully</hi> in his booke <hi>de Republica,</hi> ſhoulde af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme of the Phenicians, that being Merchants,<note place="margin">Tully. Cor. Agryp</note> they by their Merchandiſe brought in couetouſnes, pride, luxurie, and al kinde of wickednes into Graecia.<note place="margin">Hier in. 3. Ser.</note> That S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Hierome</hi> on the third of <hi>Ieremy,</hi> calleth the
<hi>Arabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> who much traded in merchandiſe, the Theeues of the world.<note place="margin">Canhag. Graecian.</note> That the
<hi>Carthaginea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> would not ſuffer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be common with their Citizens. That the <hi>Graecians</hi> would not let them enter their Citty, but cauſed them to keepe their markets without the ſuburbs, as <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Agrippa</hi> obſerueth, that <hi>Plato</hi> admitted them not into his Common wealth.<note place="margin">Cor. Agryp</note> That <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> deteſted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and their life,<note place="margin">Plato. Art. Lawes. Cicero.</note> that the ancient lawes did not admit any marchant to beare anie office, or to be admitted into the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel or Senate, that <hi>Cicero</hi> affirmeth their get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of money to be moſt odious, giuing this reaſon
<hi>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil proficiunt niſiquodammodo mentiuntur,</hi> that they get their liuing by lying. I hope the marchants of our time, deſerue not to be ſo thought of, manie of theſe marchants were <hi>Iewes, Gentiles, Heathens, Infidells, Pirats, Robbers,</hi> I hope none ſuch are to bee found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, for you are Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, I hope there be ſome
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15633:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſuch marchants amongſt you,<note place="margin">Theophr. zuingl. Theat. mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> di. Apolonius</note> as thoſe of whome <hi>Theophraſtus</hi> teſtifieth <hi>Thuriaci exercentes mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caturam abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> omni dolo vendunt omnia.</hi> Some ſuch as <hi>Apolonius,</hi> who hauing long vſed Marchandiſe at the laſt became a Phiſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the poore &amp; needy &amp; beſtowing al his time and ſtore in prouiding neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, for poore, aged, lame, blind people. Some ſuch as that famous founder of that worthie houſe of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Iohns Coll in Oxford</hi> by whoſe godly care &amp; liberal maintenance,<note place="margin">S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Th. Whit</note> many Reuerend, Learned, and religious, haue beene raiſed vp in the Church, and common wealth, I meane S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Thomas VVhite,</hi> who no doubt hath receiued the bleſſing of the promiſe to be cloathed in <hi>white array,</hi> to receiue a <hi>white stone,</hi> and in that ſtone a new name, which no man can read, but he that receiueth it: ſome ſuch merchants to be found among you as that worthie <hi>Burſer</hi> of the <hi>Exchange,</hi> the beautifier of your Cittie, and founder of that little <hi>Academy Greſham houſe,</hi> by whoſe loue to learning &amp; eternal honour to himſelfe,<note place="margin">S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Th. Greſ</note> he hath built a place, and prouided for euer a large penſion for the Readers of
<hi>Divinity, Law, Phyſicke, Logicke, Rhetoricke, Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy.</hi> Nay I doubt not, but there be manie amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt you who hauing ſought with this Merchant <hi>good Pearles,</hi> the glorie of God, and the bleſſing of his Church, and Commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealth, haue had your hands in the building of hoſpitals, ſpittle houſes, bridges, Schooles, &amp; main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of <hi>poore Schollers at the Vniverſity.</hi> If there bee ſuch <hi>wiſe, carefull,</hi> merchants amongſt you, then I can aſſure you, you are free with the Chriſtian Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant in my Text, that ſeeketh <hi>good Pearles.</hi> And I
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15633:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>woulde to God that euerie one that heareth mee this daie, were ſuch a Merchant, I can aſſure you it would be no hindera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to your trade, if as the world is the ſea ſo our
<hi>bodies</hi> were the <hi>ſhips,</hi> our <hi>Conſciences</hi> the
<hi>Pilots,</hi> our <hi>heart</hi> the <hi>compaſſe,</hi> our
<hi>faith</hi> the <hi>ſterne,</hi> our <hi>hope</hi> the <hi>Anchor,</hi> our <hi>praiers</hi> the <hi>Merchandiſe,</hi> our <hi>good works</hi> the
<hi>oares,</hi> our <hi>Country</hi> to trade in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> our
<hi>haven heauen,</hi> that at length with the good Merchant ſeeking good Pearls, we might find that goodly Pearle.</p>
            <p>And ſo I come to the 2. part of my text, <hi>which ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth good pearles, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Gen. par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Tully.</note> Heere is a perſonal diſtinction, a Merchant that ſeeketh good Pearles, <hi>Tully</hi> obſerueth a diuerſity of Marchandiſe and Marchants, and vſeth the word
<hi>negotiator aerarius, ferrarius, vinarius</hi> as we ſay a Marchant Taylor, Marchant venturer, Marcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Vintner, Marchant Jeweller, as here a Marchant that ſeeketh good Pearles. A Lapidary, a Jeweler, for every Marcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſeeketh not pearles, but they that haue know ledge in pearles. In the 21. of the <hi>Revelation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reuel. 21.</note> wee ſhal finde that the ſpirit of God ſetteth forth the heauenlie <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> with al the glorie, and luſtre, and ſplendor, that it is poſſible to be thought for the length, and the breadth, and the building, &amp; compaſſe, and the wals, and the gates, and the ſtreetes, and the foundations, that the Citty had 12. gates, and at the gates 12. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, and the names of the 12. Tribes of the children of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> and the wal of the Citty had 12. foundations, &amp; in them the names of the 12. Apoſtles, that the 12. gates were 12. pearles, and the 12. foundations were garniſhed with all precious pearles, being the ſame kinde of pearles, which were in the high Prieſts breſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate,
<pb facs="tcp:15633:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Exod.</hi> 28.15 or thoſe wherewith the K. of Tyrus was decked. <hi>Ezec.</hi> 28.13. as the 70. Interpreters ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue. Many Alluſions, allegories, compariſons, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudes, and paraliſmes, are drawne out of theſe 12. ſtones, and applied to the 12.
<hi>Patriarches,</hi> 12. <hi>Prophets</hi> 12. <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> 12.
<hi>Tribes,</hi> and at the leſt, 12. times 12. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations of theſe
12. ſtones, but I will not follow them.</p>
            <p>Our marchant ſeeketh good pearles. I might here ſtand vpon the colour, ſplendour, luſtre, nature, effect and forme of pearles: The learned knowe their colour to be diuers, their ſplendor to be gratious, their luſtre glorious, their nature and effect miraculous, their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bicular forme moſt perſit, &amp; ſurely manie great won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders hath God made knowne vnto men, in precious pearles, but the time J haue to ſpend is precious and J muſt not linger longer in theſe. By good pearls in my text,
<hi>Auendanus</hi> vnderſtandeth <hi>virtutes animi, Alber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tui legem &amp; Prophetas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Avend. Albertus, Hierome.</note> 
               <hi>Hierome caeleſtia dona,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers diuerſty doe expound theſe words, but the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per doctrine ariſing naturally, is this, that it is a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians part to ſeeke the beſt things. The reaſon of this doctrine is drawne
<hi>ab vniuerſali,</hi> al things doe deſire that which is good,<note place="margin">3. Doct. ib vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſali.</note> &amp; therfore of al, a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought to deſire it, and to endeauour to obtaine it. Not that which is good in opinion only, for ſo good may bee euil, and euil good, not good in imagination only, for ſo light maie be darkneſſe, and darkneſſe light, ſweet maie be ſower, and ſower ſweet. But good indeed <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num qua bonum.</hi> The difference that men haue made of Good is infinite. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Auſten</hi> in his
15. book <hi>de Ciuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te
<pb facs="tcp:15633:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>Dei</hi> out of <hi>Varro</hi> collecteth 288. opinions that men had concerning the ſummitie of goodnes.<note place="margin">Aug. 288. opinions Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good</note> Soe much men haue differed, ſome in miſſing of their good in reaſon, ſome in religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſome impropriating the name of good to bad, of bad to good.</p>
            <p>The philoſophers vanity excepted, none were more vaine and vile in this then the <hi>Heretickes,</hi> of all ages whoe profeſſed that their religion was only true and good, the reſt were moſt abhorrent and falſe.<note place="margin">Arians Soc</note> The <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> as
<hi>Socrates</hi> recordeth, affirmed that their religion was only good and al others falſe.<note place="margin">Ebion Epi. Hereſ. 30. Neſt. Theo.</note>
               <hi>Ebio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> as <hi>Epiphanius</hi> recordeth beeing a <hi>Samaritan</hi> yet would bee called a <hi>Chriſtian, Neſtorius</hi> as <hi>Theodoret</hi> witneſſeth, ſeeking to couer religion with the name of truth, when it was falſe and lewd.<note place="margin">The Turke Sozom. Ec. hiſt. lib. 6. c.
38.</note> The <hi>Turkes</hi> as <hi>Sozomen</hi> recordeth, comming lineally from <hi>Agar</hi> wilbe called <hi>Sarazens</hi> of <hi>Sara.</hi> The ſcripture hath taught vs that there be ſome that cry <hi>Templum Domini Templum Domini,</hi> and yet would deſtroie <hi>Dominum Templi.</hi> Ier.
7.4. That there bee ſome that call themſelues the ſeed of
<hi>Abraham</hi> that bee malitious <hi>Phariſies</hi> Ioh. 8.39. That there bee ſome that call themſelues <hi>Iewes,</hi> that are but the
<hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue of Sathan. Apoc.</hi> 3.9. That there bee ſome that had
<hi>Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> to their father, &amp; yet are not <hi>Iſrae. lites. Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> 9.7. That there are ſome that haue the name of <hi>Ieſuits,</hi> yet haue no part of the faith of truth or pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſion of <hi>Ieſus.</hi> Some alſo I feare that are called <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> that haue noe part or portion in <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Thus hath Sathan maſked folley in the habit of wiſdome, faſſhood in the habit of truth, vice in the habit of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, ſinne in the habit of godlineſſe, lewdneſſe in the
<pb facs="tcp:15633:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>habit of goodneſſe and as <hi>Polidor Virgil</hi> hath obſeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the <hi>Romiſh Church</hi> in electing their
<hi>Popes</hi> if anie were fearful they would cal him <hi>Leo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>virg.</note> If any cruel,
<hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens,</hi> if anie wicked <hi>Pius,</hi> if any couetous
<hi>Bonifacius,</hi> if anie moſt vile <hi>Innocentius.</hi> So hath good beene eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed bad, and bad good, and ſo many haue decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued themſelues in the ſeeking of good pearles.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> The vſe of this doctrine, is to warne al true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, that they follow not the <hi>ignis fatuus</hi> of lewdneſſe vnder the name of goodneſſe.! O beloued how many there be whoſe hopes and deſiers, &amp; labours, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauours doe only lead to the attaining of viſe &amp; tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitorie, earthly, momentarie, falſe, affected pleaſures, and delights! Which as <hi>Meteors,</hi> or
<hi>Comets,</hi> haue their local beeing for a time, but after vaniſh and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue. Take the counſel of <hi>Dauid</hi> ſeeke peace, ſeek that which is good,<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.</note> and dwel for euer more in the Land of of the liuing, ſo ſhal you be ſure to ſeeke good pearles.</p>
            <p>And ſo I come to the words following, <hi>and having found one pearle of great price, &amp;c.</hi> the <hi>ſecunda ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dae</hi> of my Text,<note place="margin">ſecunda. ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundae.</note> The anchor of our truſt, &amp; the author of our truth, in the 7. of <hi>Mathew</hi> promiſeth, that if we aſke, ſeeke, knocke, we ſhal receiue, finde, it ſhal be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto vs. Who then would not aſke, ſeeke, knocke, aſke with the mouth, knocke with the hand, and ſeeke with the hart? The Merchant here hauing ſought, fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, ſeeking many, findeth one, ſeeking good pearles, findeth one goodly Pearle, <hi>vnionum vnionem marga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritarum margaritam,</hi> a pearle of great price. <hi>In pretio pretium nunc est.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, Avend.</note> Some of the Fathers vnderſtande this pearle to be Charitie, and Loue, which is indeede
<pb facs="tcp:15633:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>the <hi>Lapis Chimicus,</hi> of al other vertues, or as one ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, the Godmother of al the reſt, as if the reſt remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnbaptized, moral vertues, for without this, faith is idle, hope a vaine preſuming, holyneſſe hipocriſie, zeale fury, and this of al others is the mother of ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, the daughter of grace, the miſtreſſe of truth, the Glaſſe of religion, the marriage Garment, and the key of Paradiſe, aboue al the reſt of the vertues <hi>Maior his,</hi>
1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. the bond of perfection, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.14. the fulfil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling of the Law, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.5. The newe and olde com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement.</p>
            <p>Containing all other vertues, as the Philoſopher witneſſeth,
<hi>ſicut cauſa vniverſalis particulares vel ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agonum tetragonum.</hi> Others expound this <hi>vnans mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garitam,</hi> to be <hi>celeſtis vitae dulcedinem,</hi> the ſweetnes of the life euerlaſting, the glory of the bleſſed, their euer laſting pleaſure, their Crowne of honor, their laurel of felicity, their inward and outward ioie, their diuine Paradiſe, their heauenly Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, their fulnes of bliſſe, the eternal comfort, the peace of God which paſſeth al vnderſtanding, when the Lord wil gather his faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful togither, and wil wipe away the <hi>teares</hi> from their
<hi>eies,</hi> and wil <hi>crowne</hi> them with <hi>glory, cloath</hi> them vvith <hi>gladnes,</hi> ſatiſfie them with exceeding <hi>ſweetnes,</hi> and make them <hi>partakers of eternall happineſſe,</hi> when they ſhal ſee the <hi>Courts</hi> of the <hi>Lord of hoſts,</hi> hauing
<hi>Palmes</hi> in their <hi>hands, Diade<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> on their <hi>heads, Haleluiah</hi> in their <hi>harts.</hi> Hauing <hi>riches</hi> without
<hi>meaſure, life</hi> without <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, light</hi> without <hi>darknes, health</hi> without <hi>ſickreſse, ioy</hi> without <hi>ending,</hi> &amp;
<hi>eternal ſolace</hi> without any <hi>inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsing.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15633:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Or as <hi>Hierome</hi> vnderſtandeth this pearle of greate price to be <hi>Sacramentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Paſsionis &amp; Reſurrectionis C.</hi> the Sacrament of the Lords Supper,<note place="margin">Hier. Soer.</note> wherein euerie Chriſtian doth acknowledge, how great bleſſings, we receiue by the death, and reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt, in that he that was libertie, was tied to make vs free, hee that was iuſtice, was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned to acquite vs, he that was life, was executed to ſaue vs, &amp; he that was the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the glory, the wiſedome, the power of his father, was defiled, derided, obſcured, deſpiſed to preſerue vs from eternal demnation.</p>
            <p>Or ſome others interpret it to be C. Ieſus as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſten,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. C. Ieſ.</note> who expounds
<hi>Margaritam</hi> here to be C. Ieſus our bleſſed ſauiour, the only begotten ſonne of God, the brightneſſe of glorie, the expreſſe character of his father, the firſt begotten of al creatures, the daie ſpru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g from an high, the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> the ſonne of
<hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> the light of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> &amp; the glorie of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <hi>Iſraell,</hi> who is become our wiſdome, &amp; righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſanctification,<note place="margin">Caietan.</note> and redemption, <hi>Sapientia in intellectu, iustitia in voluntate, Sanctificatio in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere, redemptio in ſtatu,</hi> wiſdome in our vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, righteouſneſſe in our wil, ſanctification in our worke, and redemption to our whole ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Anchora ſpei, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uis fidei, terrae ſal, caeli Sol, &amp; animae ſalus,</hi> the Anchor of our hope, the ſhip of our faith, the ſalt of our earth, the ſunne of our heauen, the ſaluation of our ſouls, C. Ieſus who was manifeſted in the fleſh, iuſtified in the ſpirit, ſeene of Angels, preached vnto the Gentiles, beleeued on in the world, and receiued to glory.</p>
            <p>The doctrine Jobſerue is this, that the true faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb facs="tcp:15633:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>man neuer reſteth vntil hee haue founde the true heauenly ſoule ſaueing wiſdome. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
               </label> The reaſon of this Doct. is drawne <hi>à fine</hi> from the end of his acquiſition, for this wiſdome is the period, the point the comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and perfection, and conſummation of his deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, this is that <hi>bdellium and Onix</hi> ſtone found in the riuer of <hi>Paradiſe Gen.</hi> 1.12. here is true wiſdome fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.13. here is the beloued found
<hi>Cant.</hi> 5.8. here the virgins haue found the ſweetneſſe of his ointment <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.2. here the ſpouſe hath found him whom her ſoule loueth <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.1. here <hi>Peter</hi> &amp; <hi>Andrewe</hi> haue found the Maiſter <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.4. Here is true wiſdome, here is the place of vnderſtanding, man knoweth not the price therof, for it is not found in the land of the liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Depth ſaith it is not in me, the ſea alſo ſaith it is not in mee. Gold ſhal not bee giuen for it, nor the wedge of the gold of <hi>Ophir</hi> ſhalbe waid with it, Nor the pretious
<hi>Onix</hi> ſtone, nor the <hi>Saphir,</hi> not the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtall,</hi> nor the <hi>Corall,</hi> nor the <hi>Gabiſh,</hi> nor the <hi>Topas of Aethiopia, Iob.</hi> 28.18.19. For it is <hi>vnionu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnio Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garitarum Margarita, a pearle of pearles, a Margarite of Margarites, a pearle of great price.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> The vſe of this doctrine is to moue vs al not to bee ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>we and negligent in labouring for ſo deere, ſo rare ſo pretious a pearle, ſeeing we knowe whoſoeuer ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth ſhal finde it. If this pearle were riches, then the couetous man would ſeeke for it, if honour then the ambitious would follow it, if glorie then the proud man would affect it, if pleaſure then the voluptuous would haue canuaſed for it, and yet beloued you ſee it is ſpiritual riches, ſpiritual glorie, ſpiritual honour, ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual
<pb facs="tcp:15633:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>pleaſure,! O let not this pearle bee caſt before ſwine, ſeeing it is certaine ſecuritie, ſecure tranquility ſafe iucunditie, happy eternity, and eternal felicitie! O then be yee wiſe, now o yee marcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of the world ſeek it, eſteeme it, reſpect it, loue it, finde it, buy it, yea rather then miſſe of it, ſell al you haue to buy it, as it followeth. He ſould al that he had and bought it.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Iſraelits</hi> when they did offer to the Temple,<note place="margin">Tertia. ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cundae.</note> al did offer, but they did not offer all, <hi>Exod</hi> 35.22. The young man in the goſpell was ready to followe Chriſt but loath to forſake al, <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.22. <hi>Anamas</hi> and
<hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phira</hi> were willing to bring a part to the Apoſtles, but they were loath to bring al, <hi>Ast.</hi> 5.3. So that the word <hi>al,</hi> marreth al, it is a hard, harſh, difficult, odious, tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous word, to ſel al. The Philoſophers in ſcorn of being entangled with the worlds pleaſures, did contemne al, <hi>Socrates</hi> went farther then any, and did vtterly deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſe al, <hi>Crates</hi> went farther then he, and did caſt awaie al. In the Goſpel <hi>Zacheus</hi> did reſtore al, <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.8. The
<hi>diſciples</hi> did forſake al, <hi>Math.</hi> 19.27. S. <hi>Paul</hi> did vily valew al. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.8. and here the Merchant ſelleth al, &amp; al this caſting away, diſpiſing, reſtoring, forſaking vily valuing al, and ſelling al, is but a giuing of al, &amp; indeed a gaining of al, for by this <hi>Socrates</hi> deſpiſing al became <hi>Crates</hi> to caſt away al, &amp; <hi>Crates</hi> by caſting away al did become
<hi>Polycrates</hi> to finde al,<note place="margin">Polycrat. Nat Hiſtor.</note> for whoſoeuer ſhal for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake houſes, or brethren, or ſiſters, or father, or mother or children, or wife, or lands for Chriſts ſake, ſhal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue an hundred fold more, and ſhal inherit euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life.<note place="margin">Tertull. in Apolog.</note> We read that
<hi>Democritus</hi> put out his eies for ſeare by ſight to bee tempted to incontinencie, of
<pb facs="tcp:15633:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Thracius,</hi> that hee cut downe his vines for feare of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing drunke with wine of them.<note place="margin">Gell. Noc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Art. 1.19. Lactant. Orig. Eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hiſt l. 6.8.</note> That <hi>Zeno</hi> put of his life as a garment, to put on immortalitie. That
<hi>Origen</hi> made himſelfe an Eunuch for the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. That the
<hi>Iewes</hi> did offer their Jewels, <hi>Exod.</hi> 35.22 <hi>Abraham</hi> was ready to offer his <hi>Iſaac, Gen.</hi> 22.19. That <hi>Matthew</hi> did leaue his cuſtome, <hi>Math.</hi> 9.9. <hi>Peter</hi> &amp; <hi>Andrew</hi> did leaue their nets, <hi>Matt.</hi> 4.26. Theſe did theſe things for g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine but al theſe did not gaine al, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they al did not giue al. Ouer Mercha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t doth deſpiſe al, contemne al, forſake al, caſt away al, offer al, leaue al, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l al, to but this one only pearle.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine </seg>
               </label> The Doctrine I here doe obſerue is this, that the Chriſtian Merchant is willing to forſake all his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, al his delights, al his follie, al his vanity, al his ſin and iniquitie to obtaine Chriſt: the reaſon of this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is drawne <hi>ab vtili,</hi> for a greater Commoditie,<note place="margin">Ab vtili.</note> who would not change? now looke how much diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence there is betwixt heauen and earth, ſo much is the gaine in the exchange.</p>
            <p>Another reaſon may be drawne <hi>à neceſſario,</hi> that neceſſarily he that wil obtaine Chriſt, muſt forſake al:<note place="margin">A neceſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rio.</note> for Chriſt wil not part ſtakes, he wil not take the moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the hart, he cannot abide <hi>Iſaac</hi> &amp;
<hi>Iſmaell</hi> in one houſe, the <hi>Arke</hi> and <hi>Dagon</hi> in one Church, <hi>holy</hi> &amp; <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane</hi> fier in one Cenſor,
<hi>Christ</hi> and <hi>Antichriſt</hi> in one <hi>Temple.</hi> For the
<hi>Apostles</hi> ground is that there is no fellowſhip betweene righteouſnes &amp; vnrighteouſnes, no communion of light with darknes, no agreement betweene the Temple of God and Idols, no Concord betweene Chriſt &amp; Belial. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.14. Now the Pearle that he buyeth is Chriſt, he ſelleth all and buyeth this.
<pb facs="tcp:15633:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>The word <hi>bought</hi> here as <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Calu.</hi> obſerueth doth not ſignifie anie Compenſation that man ſhould yeeld to God for attaining eternal life,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lu</note> for C. proclamation as it were in the beginning of a faire is, Ho euery on that thirſteth come to the waters of life, and yee that haue no ſiluer come, buy and eate, buy I ſaie wine, &amp; milke, without ſiluer &amp; without monie,
<hi>Eſay,</hi> 55.1.</p>
            <p>S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> vpon the 6. <hi>of Luke</hi> obſerueth this,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nbr. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>k.
6.</note> 
               <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus vult ſe vilem aeſtimari vt ab omnibus ematur, ne quis pauper deterreatur.</hi> And ſurely beloued wel is it that C. is not to bee bought of vs. For ſuch is the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrifteneſſe of Chriſtianity, that if we haue any good, any goodneſſe, any ſpirituall treaſure, anie precious pearle, any portion of land in the land of the liuing, we are ready to ſel it, either to the diuel, the world, or the ſteſh, thoſe common purchaſers. And I am ſure it Chriſt were to be bought and ſold, we ſhould rather ſel him, then buy him.</p>
            <p>When God came into the world to ſaue man, ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> went about to deſtroy God; when God came to buy man, with the deereſt drops of his blood, man went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to ſel God, for 30. peeces of ſiluer, he that came into the world to <hi>ſanctifie</hi> it with his <hi>iustice,</hi> to <hi>enrich</hi> it with his <hi>grace,</hi> to <hi>inſtruct</hi> it with his
<hi>doctrine,</hi> to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme</hi> it with his <hi>blood,</hi> to
<hi>confirme</hi> it with his <hi>example,</hi> he is ſold for 30.
<hi>peeces</hi> of ſiluer, more vily valued then the baſeſt beaſts, that they ſold in their market. I feare me that there be now as cunning buyers, &amp; ſellers, as ſkilful <hi>Merchants</hi> as euer there were, euen ſuch as would ſel <hi>Heaven, Angels, Saints, Seraphins,</hi> nay
<hi>God him ſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15633:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Who liueth amongſt vs and knoweth not our <hi>mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant Diuines,</hi> who being <hi>Ephraimiticall</hi> Tempori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zers wil ſel the libertie of a good conſcience, for fauor &amp; preferme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t? who knoweth not our <hi>Marchant Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers</hi> who not only ſel their labours but the lawes and Juſtice it ſelfe? Who knoweth not our <hi>Marchant Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions</hi> who ſel <hi>ignorance, vnſkillfulnes, great words,</hi> &amp;
<hi>vnſufficient druggs?</hi> Who knoweth not our <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant vſerer</hi> who (againſt ſo many <hi>places</hi> of <hi>ſcripture,</hi> the iudgment of al the <hi>ancient fathers,</hi> the <hi>Canon,</hi> and <hi>Ciuil</hi> lawes, the <hi>conſtitutions</hi> of al good <hi>Commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> welths,</hi> the
<hi>reaſons</hi> of <hi>heathen Philoſophers,</hi> the <hi>counſell</hi> of the <hi>ſchoolmen,</hi> and the <hi>opinion</hi> of al our
<hi>Diuines</hi> except they bee <hi>vſerers</hi>) knoweth that vſerie is condemned, as vncharitable, and Antichriſtian, and yet this biter, ſets his
<hi>ſoule</hi> at <hi>ſale,</hi> &amp; <hi>receiues quarter rent for his ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation?</hi> Who knoweth not our marcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t monopoliſts who by groſſe ingroſſing &amp; by art &amp; cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning doe ariſe the price of commodities which by ordinary courſe would be much cheaper, &amp; ſo againſt the laws &amp; cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of al Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealths, they are the pilling, polling, Caterpillers of the Common wealth? For if euer of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie it were true, it is of them <hi>vivitur ex rapto.</hi> Here might I put vp a <hi>Siquis</hi> for
<hi>cruel Ahabs, churliſh Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bals, De populating Landlords, incloaſing Cormorants, Simoniacall Patrons, and Church-robbing Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezers.</hi> O thoſe monſters of men, contemners of God, impious, ſacrilegious Church-robbers, irreligious <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lianiſts,</hi> which do rifle and ſpoile Churches of the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments, and other riches, lands, &amp; reuenews, which were giuen vnto God to maintaine his houſe &amp; houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold.
<pb facs="tcp:15633:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>That whereas Churches in
<hi>Chryſoſtomes</hi> time were <hi>Regijs aulis clariora,</hi> now
<hi>Caneſcunt turpi templa relicta ſitu.</hi> That wheras ſometimes the
<hi>Iews</hi> brought more to the founding of the <hi>Tabernacle</hi> then
<hi>Moyſes</hi> would; now <hi>Chriſtians</hi> take from the
<hi>Temple</hi> more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euer <hi>Iewes, Gentiles, Heathens, Pagans,</hi> or
<hi>Infidells</hi> would, That wheras ſomtimes they were houſes of praier, nowe they are become dens of theeues, that wheras ſomtimes the price of a dogg or the hire of a whore, might not bee brought into the Temple, now the price of the Temple is brought to maintaine doggs, and whores &amp;c. And Temples made ſtables, Shipcoates, ſtore houſes for wool, hogſties, Barnes, maulthouſes, Alehouſes, nay worſe then al this, if this be not the abomination of deſolation what is? O Lord thus haue they defiled thy Temple, and made <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> a heape of ſtones. Lord take thy owne cauſe in hand thou didſt driue the byers and ſellers out of the Temple. O what hadſt thou done if they had been by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and ſellers of the Temple?</p>
            <p>I knowe notwithſtanding the general, &amp; iuſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint againſt the corrupt cuſtome of many Simoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acal Patrons, that the Lord hath reſerued for himſelfe a remnant who in honour of learning and care of the glory of God haue made choice of ſchollers from the Vniuerſitie (to inioie the ſpiritual preferments, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they were <hi>Doners.</hi>) who might otherwiſe long haue waited at the poole vntil Angels had put the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in. I muſt confeſſe Gods fauour to my ſelfe in this, and the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy minde of an honorable Patrone;<note place="margin">Thomas
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>erley of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iſton</note> the Lord reward him and his, according to their own deſire. Preſidents
<pb facs="tcp:15633:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>of this kind be miracles in our age, wherin the abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of deſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath got the vpper hand. Let it for ever bee worthy the obſeruation, I ſay worthie the obſeruation to the terrour of theſe diuils, that <hi>Nabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezar, Balthaſar, Antiochus, Helidorus, Pompei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius Magnus, Marcus Craſſus</hi> had vnhappy ſucceſſe and moſt of them died miſerably by reaſon of their ſacrilegious Church robbing: and it was wel obſerued 500. years ſince <hi>ſpiritualiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> venditores ſemper egeſtate confundi,</hi> that the pinchers of ſpiritual things are at laſt pinched with extreame penurie; if euer by ſimony or ſacriledge they come to anie true profit let me for euer bee branded with the name of a falſe Prophet. Curſed bee ſuch ſeeking, finding, buying, ſelling, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſing, when God and his Church are robbed.</p>
            <p>Beloued we haue not learned C. ſo and therfore let euerie of vs make this vſe to beware of the <hi>execrable things</hi> not to ſet our ſelues at ſale, to commit iniquity, to ſet at ſale our truth, honeſtie, conſcience, oaths, ſoules, and ſaluation, by bryberie, forgery, periurie, hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, ſimony, or ſacriledg: the name of ſuch things ſhould not be hard amongſt vs as becommeth <hi>Saints;</hi> the practiſe hereof is the <hi>myſterie of iniquitie,</hi> and the practiſers hereof they be the diuels tradeſ-men.</p>
            <p>I ſhould now make ſome application of that hath bin ſaid vnto the purpoſe, and time preſent, but the <hi>time preſent,</hi> doth not afford mee time, to ſtaie here vpon, and it is but in vaine to ad precept vpon precept, and line vpon line, ſeeing you obſerue nether rule, nor line It wil be the more to your <hi>condemnation,</hi> if I ſhoulde ſtand vpon anie further <hi>application.</hi> For howe ſhal I
<pb facs="tcp:15633:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>thinke to ſpeed in gayning of you when ſo manie, ſo heauenly, ſo powerful meſſengers, haue bin ſent to you that haue <hi>nailed</hi> your ſinnes often to this <hi>Croſse</hi> with the
<hi>hammer of the word</hi> and yet they bee as many, as mightie, as bloody, as ſilthie, as crying, as feareful, as euer they were. Notwithſtanding my ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in a word ſhalbe firſt to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xhor.</note> that at this time are aſſembled at this great faire, or Mart, or Market, that they by lying, ſwearing, forſwearing, ſel not them ſelues to Sathan, but that they make a Conſcience of their words, works, oathes, aſſeuerations, proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that in a greedines of gaine they cal not God to witnes, for the prices of their wares againſt their truth their oath, Conſcience, and knowledge. O beloued, ſel not ſoule<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> &amp; ſaluation, looſe not the ſubſtance for the Accident, heauen for earth, that which wil neuer pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, for that which doth periſh. Laſtly, my exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in a word is to this City in general. O <hi>London</hi> thou that ſitteſt like a Queene, al thy Citize<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s being as ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nie Mercha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, thy Merchta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s as ſo many Princes nay, as ſo many poliſhed corners of the Temple. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber them, that for al their port, and ſtate<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and dignitie, &amp; riches, They are vnworthy to enioie the leſt of theſe bleſſings, vnleſſe they be like to that good Merchant here that ſeeketh good pearles, their careleſnes, hau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines, oppreſſion, wickednes, are but the wormes and moathes of their greatnes, &amp; theſe wormes &amp; moaths wil corrupt them, and their greatnes. Neither they, nor thou, ſhalt ſinne with impunity, the mightines of thy ſtate, ſingularitie of thy gouernment, climing of thy wals, aſpiring of thy Towers, multitude of thy
<pb facs="tcp:15633:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>people, cannot make thee ſecure againſt the wrath of the Lord. Thought thou were a Citty of Palme trees as <hi>Iericho</hi> or the ioy of the world, as <hi>Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> or the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous &amp; populous Citty of earth, as <hi>Babilon</hi> or the mart of the Nations, as
<hi>Tyrus,</hi> whoſe Mercha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts were Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and their Chapmen the nobles of the world, yet the time may come, that thou maiſt ſay, I was a Queen I ſit now as a widdow, becauſe I haue not remembred the day of my viſitation. The L. may ſtaine the pride of thy glorie and bring to contempt al thy honourable. in al the ſtories, either rude, or polite, prophane or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, I finde no Citty more honored for Merchants &amp; Mercha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>diſe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Tyrus in the prophecie of <hi>Ezec.</hi> They of <hi>Iauan Tuball</hi> &amp;
<hi>Meſhech</hi> were her Mercha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts.<note place="margin">Ezech. 27.</note> They of <hi>Togarmah</hi> and <hi>Dedan</hi> were her Merchants. They of
<hi>Aram</hi> &amp; <hi>Damaſcus</hi> were her Merchants. They of
<hi>Iuda</hi> and of <hi>Iſraell</hi> were her Merchants. They of
<hi>Sheba</hi> and <hi>Ramah</hi> were her Merchants. They of <hi>Haram</hi> &amp; <hi>Cameh</hi> and <hi>Eden</hi> of <hi>Sheba, Aſher,</hi> and
<hi>Chilmad</hi> were her Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, &amp; they did bring faire horſes and mules, &amp; V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicornes hornes and Peacocks, and Emeralds, purple and broidered worke, and fine linen, and pearle, &amp; Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and wheat, and wine, and hony, and oile, &amp; bawm, &amp; Caſſia, &amp; Calamus the cheefe of al ſpices, of al pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cious ſtones, &amp; gold, &amp; raiments of blew ſilke, &amp; broi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered works, &amp; rich apparel. So that by her Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe ſhee was repleniſhed and made glorious in the middeſt of the ſea. And yet for al this, in the end of the chapter, the L. threatneth this feareful deſolation to Tyrus for her abominable ſinnes. Thy riches, and thy faires, thy Merchandiſe thy mariners, thy Pilots, thy
<pb facs="tcp:15633:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>Calkers, and al the occupiers of thy merchandiſe, &amp; al the men of war that are in thee, and al the multitude which is in the middeſt of thee ſhal fall in the middeſt of the ſea, in the daie of thy ruine. Thy ſuburbs ſhal ſhake at the ſound of the crie of the Pilots, &amp; in their mourning they ſhal take vp this lamentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, what Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is like vnto <hi>Tyrus</hi> ſo deſtroied, and the marchants amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the people ſhal hiſſe at thee thou ſhalt be a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and neuer ſhalt be any more. Beloued it is a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible, fearful vnſpeakable iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. But you ſee great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſins wil ſhake the foundations of the greateſt city vpon the earth, and though their heads ſtood a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the ſtarrs, yet he is able to bring them into the duſt and rubble; multitude of offences wil conſume multitudes of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; you know many thouſands thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands haue beene ſwept away in your Citie. The daies can ſpeake &amp; the yeares can witneſſe, how the plague hath beene a leidger for manie yeares amongſt you.</p>
            <p>O my beloued in the bowels of C. Ieſus. at the length remember that the feare of the Lord is your ſafeſt refuge, righteouſneſſe your ſtrongeſt bulwarke, ſobrietie and ſanctimonie of life your wales of Braſſe, Pietie your beſt pearle, C. Ieſus your beſt Iewel. O then ſeek, ſearch, labour, endeauor, find, buy this pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rle, this peace, marchandiſe in this til hee come that wil come to iudge the quick and the dead! The Lorde make you rich in his wiſdome, &amp; make you al wiſe in Chriſt Jeſus. <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:15633:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
